Now, how do we actually deploy this fund me contract?
现在，我们该如何部署这个 "FundMe" 合约呢？
Well, let's think about this for a little bit.
让我们来仔细考虑一下这个问题
When working with remix, it was pretty easy, right?
当我们使用 Remix 的时候，这是件很简单的事，对吧？
We just deployed it to a test net.
我们只要直接把它部署到测试网络上就行了
Ah, that's kind of the issue there, isn't it
啊，但这就是问题所在不是么？
deploying to a rink, the test net is a little bit slow.
部署到 Rinkeby 测试网上实在是有点慢
We don't always want to have to deploy to one of these slow test nets or even a main net
我们不想总是在这些慢速的测试网或主网上进行部署
when tinkering and fiddling with our contracts, do we
从而调试和修改我们的合约，是吧？
know that's gonna be really bad,
是的，那真的很糟糕
we really want to deploy to a test net as a last stop after we've done all our testing locally.
我们想要的是将部署测试网这一步作为本地测试之后的最后一步
Or we can deploy it to a test that to see some very specific code work,
或者我们可以提前将其部署到测试网络以查看某些特定代码如何工作
like for example, with the chain link documentation.
例如与 Chainlink 文档一起使用
So ideally, we deploy this to a local network first. But can we just do that?
理想情况下，我们应当首先部署到本地网络上，但我们真的可以直接这样做么？
Well, if we look in our price converter, dot Seoul,
如果查看一下我们的 "PriceConverter.sol"
we have this hard coded address in here, this 0x address,
我们会发现这里有一处硬编码地址，就是这个 0x 地址
if we go to Doc's dot chain that link EVM chains, contract addresses for Aetherium data feeds.
如果我们前往 "docs.chain.link"->"EVM Chains"->"Contract Address"->"Ethereum Data Feeds"
That address is the eth USD, specifically for Rinkeby.
那个地址是 "ETH USD" 的地址，具体来说是 Rinkeby 的
What if we work on the Hard Hat Network?
如果我们想在 "Hardhat Network" 上运行呢
Example? default network? Hard Hat.
比如说 `defaultNetwork: "Hardhat"`
And then like I said before,
就像我之前说的
if you don't write this in part, it is automatically the default network.
如果你这里不明确指定，那么 "hardhat" 将自动作为默认网络使用
But if we're to point to the Hard Hat Network,
但如果我们就要指向 "Hardhat Network"
harder network is a blank blockchain.
"Hardhat Network" 是一个空白的区块链
And it gets destroyed every time our scripts finish,
每次我们的脚本运行完毕后它都会被销毁
or even if we're working with a local node,
又或者即使我们在本地节点上工作
this price feed contract won't exist,
这个喂价 (price feed) 合约也都是不存在的
one of the code there won't be updated with data. So what do we do?
其中某些代码将无法更新数据，那么我们该怎么办？
How do we test and interact with our code locally? Is there a way we can do this?
我们该如何在本地测试中与我们的代码进行交互？有没有什么方式可以做到这一点？
Well, one of the ways that we can do this that we'll learn a little bit later
嗯，之后我们会学习一种方法
is actually forking a blockchain, where you can keep stuff hard coded.
就是所谓的分叉(fork)一个区块链，你可以在其中保留硬编码内容
But usually, it's still better to figure out how to do everything with something called mocks.
但通常来说，最好的方法还是使用一种被称为 "mocks" 的方法来完成所有的操作
There's a great Stack Overflow question that just says, What is mocking
这里有一个很好的 "Stack Overflow" 问题问的就是，什么是 Mocking？
and mocking is primarily used for unit testing, which we'll talk about in a little bit.
mocking 主要用于单元测试，我们稍后会详细讨论
And object under test may have dependencies on other complex objects.
受测对象可能依赖于其它复杂的对象
To isolate the behavior of the object,
为了隔离某些对象的行为
you want to replace other objects by mocks that simulate the behavior of the real objects.
你需要使用 mocks 对象来替换其它对象，以模拟真实对象的行为
In short, mocking is creating objects that simulate behavior of real objects.
简而言之，mocking 就是创建一个模拟真实对象行为的对象
Now, this might seem like a lot of words.
看起来它说了很多东西
But basically, what we want to do is we want to make a fake price feed contract
但基本来说，我们想要的就是一个虚拟的喂价合约
that we can use and we can control when working locally.
以供我们在本地工作时能够使用并进行控制
So back here, I'm just going to leave a note in here saying,
所以在这里，我会留下一条注释说
When going for local host or Hard Hat Network, we want to use a mock.
当使用本地主机或 "Hardhat Network" 时，我们要使用 mock
Okay, great, well, we can use a mock
OK 好，现在我们要使用 mock 了
and we'll learn how to make one of those in a little bit.
之后我们将学习如何来创建一个 mock
Well, what happens when we want to change chains,
但是当我们想切换链的时候会发生什么呢
for example, back in dots dot chain to link EVM chains, contract addresses,
举个例子，回到 "docs.chain.link"->"EVM Chains"->"Contract Address"
there are a ton of different block chains that have price feeds on them.
这里有很多不同的区块链它们都有喂价数据
And on each one of these blockchains,
并且在这些区块链的每一个上面
the eth USD price feed is going to be a little bit different.
"ETH/USD" 的喂价数据可能会有一点不同
For example, we're looking at ETH USD,
比方说，如果你查看 "ETH/USD"
the address of eth USD for Aetherium main net
以太坊主网的 "ETH/USD" 地址
is different from the address of eth USD for Rigby,
与 Rinkeby 的 "ETH/USD" 地址是不同的
which makes sense, they're totally different contracts on different chains,
这是有道理的，它们是不同链上完全不同的合约
they have very similar functionality. And they do nearly the exact same thing.
它们有非常相似的功能，做的也几乎是完全相同的事
But they're still different.
但它们仍然是不同的
We're also going to need a way for us to modularize or parameterize, this address in here,
我们还需要一种方法来把这里的地址给模块化或参数化
so that no matter what chain we deploy to,
这样无论我们部署到哪个链上
we don't have to change any of our code,
我们都不需要改动任何代码
we can always have our code be exactly the same.
这样我们的代码可以始终保持一致
And we don't have to come in here and like flip values and flip variables and stuff. So
也就不需要到这儿来切换值和切换变量之类的
let's keep that all of that in mind as we write the rest of this.
在我们编写接下来的代码时，我们需要牢记这一点
Now in order to parameterize. This,
现在，为了把它参数化
we actually want to prioritize and do a little refactoring of our fundamental soul.
我们需要对我们的 "FundMe.sol" 进行一些重构
Refactoring basically means going back and,
重构的意思基本上就是
and changing the way your code works.
回过头去改变你代码的工作方式
Right now we have this constructor function, right
现在我们拥有这个构造函数，对吧？
the constructor function is the function that automatically gets called whenever we deploy our contract.
构造函数就是一个在我们部署合约时会被自动调用的函数
Right now it's not doing a whole lot
目前它并没有做很多事情
right now it's just updating the owner variable to be whoever sent in the contract.
现在它只负责把 "owner" 变量更新为合约的发送者
But we can actually have a do much more than that.
但我们能做的远远不止这些
Since this constructor is a function just like every other function, we can actually have it take parameters,
由于构造函数和其它函数一样，也可以接收参数
one of the parameters that we might like for it to have is going to be the address of a price feed.
那么我们想让它接收的其中一个可能的参数就是价格数据的地址
So let's go ahead and add this and figure out how to refactor all this code.
现在让我们添加这个参数，并搞清楚如何重构这些代码
So we're going to add constructor address, price feed for the constructor in here.
所以我们要在 "constructor" 中添加一个 "address priceFeed"
When we deploy our contract. Now
现在，当我们部署合约时
we're going to pass it the eth USD price feed address depending on what chain we're on.
我们将根据所在的链向它传递 "ETH/USD" 的喂价地址
If we're on rink B, we'll use this address
如果我们在 Rinkeby 上，我们就要用这个地址
if one polygon will use a different one
如果是 Polygon 就会用其它的
b&b, different one, Gnosis hecho, avalanche, etc, you get the picture.
BNB 也是一个道理 Gnosis, HECO, Avalanche 等等，你应该懂了吧
So we're going to marginalize this like so.
所以我们才要这样调整它
Now that our constructor takes a parameter for the price feed,
现在我们的 "constructor" 要接收一个 "priceFeed" 参数
we can actually save an aggregator v3 interface object as a global variable
那么我们就可以将 "AggregatorV3Interface" 保存为一个全局变量
in our price converter,
在我们的 "PriceConverter" 中
we just create a price feed variable of type aggregator v3 interface,
我们创建了一个 "AggregatorV3Interface" 类型的 "priceFeed" 变量
which again, we're importing from the chainlink repo,
并且重申一下，我们是从 chainlink 的代码库中导入进来的
which is an interface object which gets compiled down to the ABI.
它是一个 "Interface" 对象并且会被编译为 ABI
If you match an ABI with up with an address, you get a contract that you can interact with.
如果你将 ABI 与某个地址匹配起来，就能获得一个可以与之交互的合约了
So we're going to do the same thing here.
我们将在这里执行相同的操作
We're gonna say, aggregate Tor, v3 interface, public price feed,
我们要定义 "AggregatorV3Interface public priceFeed"
ration and call this price feed address
这里得改成 "priceFeedAddress"
so that these don't have the same name.
这样它们就不会重名了
And in our constructor, we're going to say price feed equals,
在 "constructor" 中，我们要执行 "priceFeed = "
and we're going to do the exact same thing we did with our price converter
接下来就和我们在 "PriceConverter" 中所做的完全相同
equals aggregate tore the three interface of price feed address.
"= AggregatorV3Interface(priceFeedAddress)"
Like so
就像这样
now, we have this price feed address
现在我们就有了这个 "priceFeedAddress"
that's variable and modularized, depending on whatever chain that we're on.
它是可变的也是模块化的，具体的值取决于我们在哪个链上
Now, what we can do is we can grab this price feed address, and we can use it for our price converter.
现在，我们就可以获取 "priceFeedAddress" 并将其用于我们的 "PriceConverter" 了
So where are we using our price converter?
那么我们要在哪里使用 "PriceConverter" 呢？
Well, just a quick reminder, we're using using price converter for you at 256.
快速提醒一下，我们正在使用 "using PriceConverter for uint256"
We're using this as a library on top of our unit 256 type.
我们将其作为一个 "library"，附着于 "uint256" 类型之上
So we're calling message dot value dot get conversion rate.
所以我们要调用 "msg.value.getConversionRate"
So we look at our price converter, we have this function get conversion rate,
查看一下我们的 "PriceConverter"，里面有这个 "getConversionRate" 函数
which takes an FML as its initial parameter,
它接收一个 "ethAmount" 作为初始参数
which again, since this is a library,
再提醒一下，由于这是一个 "library"
it automatically passes the message dot value into this get conversion rate function.
所以它会自动将 "msg.value" 传递给 "getConversionRate" 函数
But we could also pass in this price feed,
但我们可以同时传递这个 "priceFeed"
and therefore we wouldn't need to hard code it in the get price anymore.
这样 "getPrice" 里就不再需要使用硬编码了
So let's go ahead and figure out how to do that.
让我们来看一下如何实现这一点
Well, what we can do is we can do message dot value dot get conversion rate,
我们需要做的是使用 `msg.value.getConversionRate`
we'll stick price feed in here.
并把 "priceFeed" 填入其中
And then we'll have to update our get conversion rate
接着要更新我们的 "getConversionRate"
to do a comma so that it takes a second parameter,
添加一个逗号，以使其接收第二个参数
because remember, again, the initial parameter is going to be message dot value.
因为要记住，初始参数是 `msg.value`
And the second parameter is going to be what we define here.
而第二个参数将是我们在此处定义的内容
So we'll do s amount, comma ag reg gate Tor v3 interface.
所以我们写下 `ethAmount, AggregatorV3Interface`
And we'll call this price feed.
并称其为 `priceFeed`
And now, when we call our get price function,
现在，当我们调用 `getPrice` 函数时
we can pass the price feed to the get price function.
就可以将 `priceFeed` 传递给 `getPrice` 函数了
And up here we can have get price.
而在这里，我们可以定义 `getPrice`
Take, you guessed it an aggregate or the three interface called price feed.
接收一个 `AggregatorV3Interface priceFeed`
And now we no longer need to hard code in the price feed.
现在我们就再也不需要在 `priceFeed` 中使用硬编码了
And we can just delete those lines and have it compile like this, which is awesome.
我们可以删掉这几行并直接进行编译，就像这样，这真是太棒了
So quick refresher, we're parameterizing that price feed address
好，快速回顾一下，我们正在对 `priceFeed` 地址进行参数化处理
and passing it in with a constructor
并将其传入构造函数中
that gets saved as a global variable to an aggregator v3 interface type,
它被保存为一个 "AggregatorV3Interface" 类型的全局变量
or passing it to a get conversion rate function,
并被传入一个 `getConversionRate` 函数
which passes it to the get price function, which then just calls latest round data.
接着被进一步传入到 `getPrice` 函数，然后调用 `latestRoundData`
And we probably could have made this even easier,
或许我们能让这一切变得更简单一些
probably could have just got rid of the get price function
我们可以直接删除 `getPrice` 函数
and stuck this code in the get conversion rate.
并把这些代码放进 `getConversionRate` 里
But we'll leave it there for now.
但我们暂时先不做改动
Now that we've done that refactoring, let's make sure it works.
现在我们已经完成了重构，让我们确保它能顺利工作
Yarn Hardhead, compile, invalid value undefined for hardhat dot config dot networks.
`yarn hardhat compile`，未在 "HardhatConfig.networks" 中定义的无效的值
Let's go to the let's go to the config real quick.
让我们快速转到配置文件
That's because the default network needs to be outside of networks. My mistake. Let's try that again.
这是因为 `defaultNetwork` 需要在 `networks` 的外部，是我的错，我们再试一次
I spelled interface wrong and the price converter.
我把 "Interface" 拼错了，在 `PriceConverter` 里
And a quick note, if gives you an error like this,
这里做个小说明，如果你像这样遇到了某个报错
oftentimes, you can command click or control click and open that file up right in the editor,
通常你可以按住 "Command" 键单击或 "Ctrl" 键单击来在编辑器中把对应文件打开
which saves you some time, we're going to have defined the line and find the file.
这样可以节省你的一些时间，也就不需要去找特定某个文件的某一行了
But yeah, let's spell that correctly.
好的，让我们把拼写改正
And let's try this again.
接着我们来再试一次
And awesome. It looks like it's compiling correctly.
太棒了，看起来编译正确
And we just have some warnings,
只是有一些警告("Warning")
it looks like these warnings are just about this git version,
看起来这些 "warning" 是关于这个 `getVersion` 的
which is because we're shadowing this, we're creating a new price variable down here,
这是因为我们在这里创建了一个新的 `priceFeed` 变量
you've no we just created a global price free variable.
而我们刚刚又在这里创建了一个全局的 `priceFeed` 变量
Let's just go ahead and delete the get version function altogether
我们把 `getVersion` 函数也删除掉
since we're not even going to really need it.
因为我们根本不需要它
And we only use the Git version to show you how to actually start working with interfaces.
我只是用 `getVersion` 来向你展示如何开始使用接口
And then we'll compile it one more time for good measure.
让我们再编译一次以确保一切顺利
Boom compiled successfully. Awesome.
嘭，编译成功，太棒了
So now we've just refactored our code.
我们刚刚已经重构了我们的代码
So we can pass a price feed address depending on the network that we're on.
这样我们就可以根据我们所处的网络来传递 `priceFeed` 的地址了
Okay, great. With all that being said, let's come back to our deploy Funmi script,
好，说了这么多，让我们回到 "deploy-fund-me" 脚本
and let's learn how to actually deploy the rest of it.
继续学习如何部署它的其余部分
In order for us to deploy a contract
为了部署这个合约
we remember from our last sections that we use the contract factories,
上一部分我们使用了 `contractFactory`
with heart hit Deploy, we can just use this deploy function.
通过 "hardhat deploy"，我们可以直接使用这个 `deploy` 函数
And to use the deploy function,
要使用这个 `deploy` 函数
we'll say const Funmi, which is going to be the name of our contract,
我们要写下 `const fundMe` 这是我们合约的名称
equals await. And we'll call this deploy function, the name of the contract that we're deploying right now,
`= await` 接着调用这个 `deploy` 函数，包含我们要部署的合约名称
and then a list of overrides that we want to add here.
以及想要添加的覆盖选项的列表
So we're gonna say who is actually deploying this by saying from,
通过指定 `from` 来确定是谁在进行部署
we're gonna say it's from the Deployer.
我们将指定 `deployer` 为 `from` 的值
We're gonna pass any arguments to the constructor In this args piece here,
我们会将任何需要传递给构造函数的参数放在 `args` 中
which we just added a single Argh.
目前我们只传递了一个参数
So these brackets, we're going to make it a list of arguments,
这个括号会使它成为一个参数列表
we're going to put the price feed address in here,
我们要在这里放入 `priceFeedAddress`
which we'll show you how to do in a second, put price feed address.
我们马上就会展示如何做到这一点，“放入 price feed address ”
And then we're also going to do some custom logging here
接着我们还要做一些自定义的日志
so that we don't have to do all that console dot log stuff that we've been doing this whole time.
这样我们就不需要像之前那样总是用一堆 `console.log` 了
And we need to put something in here.
我们需要在这里放置一些内容
We need to put an address in here.
我们需要放在这里的是一个地址
And you can use this backslash star to put like a common in between your code.
你可以使用这个反斜杠星号("/*")在你的代码中放置注释
We can't just do const address equals, you know the address and stick it in here.
我们不能直接用 `const address = `，因为你要把地址放到这里
Well, I mean, we could but we're not really prioritizing now. Right?
好吧，我的意思是，可以这样做，但这样就不是真正的参数化了，对吧？
We're kind of back to just hard coding it here.
这相当于我们又回到硬编码了
So what can we do instead?
那我们该怎么做呢？
Well, what we can do is we can actually use the chain ID to do something like
我们可以使用 "chainId"，来做一些像是这样的事
if chain ID is x, use address, Y,
如果 "chainId" 是 "X" 则使用地址 "Y"
or if chain ID is Z use address A.
或者如果 "chainId" 是 "Z" 则使用地址 "A"
So we can do something that looks like this.
那么我们可以做一些类似这样的事情
And to enable this functionality, we actually take a page out of the Ave GitHub.
要想实现这个功能，我们需要借鉴 "aave" 的 GitHub
So Ave is another protocol that's on multiple chains
"aave" 是存在于多个链上的一个协议
and has to deploy their code to multiple chains and work with multiple different addresses.
所以它必须把代码部署到多个链上并使用多个不同的地址
So what they do is they use a number of different useful tricks.
他们使用了多个不同的实用技巧
But one of the main ones is using this helper hardhat config.
其中一个主要的就是使用这个 "helper-hardhat-config"
Now they're using TypeScript with JavaScript, but it's gonna be the same thing.
他们用的是 TypeScript 我们用的是 JavaScript，但都是一样的
With this config, they have different variables,
在这个 config 中，他们定义了许多不同的变量
depending on what network that they're actually on.
具体取决于它们所依赖的网络
And depending on the network that they're on, they use different variables.
根据所在网络的不同，他们使用不同的变量
So they use this network config almost to do exactly what we're trying to do here.
他们使用的这个网络配置几乎完全做到了我们想要做的事情
So what we want to do is we're going to create a new file at the root directory,
那么我们要做的就是，在根目录下创建一个新的文件
so just click down here, new file.
点击这里，新建文件(New File)
And we're going to call it helper, hard hat config dot j, s.
将其命名为 "helper-hardhat-config.js"
And this is where we're going to define that network config.
这就是我们要定义网络配置的地方
And this is where we're going to say, hey, if you're on network, a, use this address
也就是告诉它，嘿，如果你在网络 A 上，就用这个地址
network, be this use this address, etc.
如果是网络 B 就是这个地址，等等等等
So we're going to create an object called const. Network config. equals
现在我们就来构建 `const networkConfig =`
and we're going to add a bunch of stuff in here.
然后在这里添加一大堆东西
So our main network that we're working with right now is rinky. dinky has a chain ID of four.
现在我们使用的网络是 Rinkeby，Rinkeby 的 chainId 是 4
So we'll say chain ID four
所以我们写下 chainId 4
is going to be named Rinkeby. And the eth USD price feed address is going to be
`name: "rinkeby"` 以及 `ethUsdPriceFeed` 地址是
the price feed address of rank B of the eth USD price feed.
Rinkeby "ETH/USD" 喂价数据的地址
So we're going to copied from the documentation or from the GitHub, whatever you want to do,
我们把它从文档中复制下来，或者 GitHub 也行，随你便了
and paste it in here.
然后粘贴到这里
Now we have a simple methodology of
现在我们就有了一个简单的方法
keeping track of different price feeds a different contract addresses across different chains.
来跟踪不同喂价数据在不同链上的不同合约地址
Let's say for example, we wanted to deploy to Polygon as well.
举个例子，比如说我还想要部署到 Polygon 上
Well, first, what are we going to need?
首先，我们需要什么？
Well, we're going to need the chain ID of polygon.
我们需要的是 Polygon 的 chainId
So a quick little Google Search brings us to the polygon documentation.
使用 Google 快速搜索一下，它会带我们去到 Polygon 的文档
And we see the chain ID is 137.
可以看到 chainId 是 137
So I'll do 137. What's a little brackets here,
所以这里就是 137 然后是一组括号
we'll say name, polygon. Then we'll do a comma eth USD, price feed.
还有 `name: "polygon", ethUsdPriceFeed`
And then we'll add the price feed of eth USD on polygon.
接着我们要添加 Polygon "ETH/USD" 的 "priceFeed"
So docstoc, chain link, polygon or Matic and then we'll look up eth, USD.
所以来到 "docs.chain.link" -> "Polygon (Matic)" 找到 "ETH/USD"
And boom, we see it right here. We've grabbed this address, and we paste it in.
可以看到就在这里，获取这个地址，并粘贴过来
Well, what about the Hardhead? Network?
那么 "Hardhat Network" 是什么样的呢
We'll get to that in just a second, don't you worry.
我们马上就会解释，不要着急
And then at the bottom, we need to export this network config.
接着来到底部，我们需要导出这个 "networkConfig"
So our other scripts can actually work with it.
以便我们的其它脚本能够使用它
So we'll do module dot exports equals network config.
所以我们要写下 `module.exports = `
And we're going to actually export a couple of things from this file,
我们还要从这个文件中导出一些其它东西
which is why we're doing it like this instead of that default way that I showed you before.
这也是为什么这里没有像之前展示的那样使用 `default` 的方式
So back in our script, now, what can we do?
回到我们的脚本，现在我们能做些什么呢？
Well, first, we want to go ahead and import that network config.
首先，我们要做的是导入网络配置
So we'll say const. Network config equals require,
所以就是 `const  = require("")`
and then we'll import it, we'll go down and directory to help our Hardhead config and save.
现在导入它，上一级目录的 `helper-hardhat-config`，然后保存
And I just want to mention this one more time, just so that it doesn't confuse anybody.
我想要再提醒一下这个，以免让人混淆
This syntax here, constant network config with the little curly braces around it
这个语法 `const ` 带有一组花括号
is the same is if I went const. Helper config equals this thing,
它就和 `const helperConfig` 等于这些东西
which helper config is now kind of this whole file.
现在 `helperConfig` 就代表了整个文件
And then const network config equals Hopper config dot network config.
然后是 `const networkConfig = helperConfig.networkConfig`
So again, this index is just kind of an easy way
所以，这个语法就是一个简便用法
to extrapolate or pull out just the network config from this file.
它会推断并提取出 `networkConfig`，从这个文件中
So that's how that works.
这就是它的工作原理
And that's why we export it at the bottom so that we can do this,
这也是为什么我们要在底部导出它的原因，就是为了做这个操作
please use the GitHub repository to ask questions and discussions
请尽情使用 GitHub 仓库来进行提问和讨论
especially about some of this JavaScript stuff.
尤其是有关 JavaScript 的这些东西
Alright, great. So now that we have this network configured here,
很好，现在我们有了这些网络配置
we can now do this part of where we say if China d z use a if chain ID is x use y.
现在我们就可以进行这个操作了 “如果 chainId 是 Z 则使用 A 如果 chainId 是 X 则使用 Y”
So Since our helper config is nicely in this kind of dictionary, key value pair style,
由于我们的 `helperConfig` 很好地使用了这种字典的键值对儿格式
what we can do is we can say const. eth USD. Price feed address equals network config at the chain ID,
所以我们可以这么做 `const ethUsdPriceFeedAddress = networkConfig[chainId]`
because if Francina D, or it'll be this object,
如果 "chainId" 是 4 那么就是这个对象
French entity polygon, it'll be this object
如果 "chainId" 是 Polygon，就会是这个对象
at the eth USD price feed,
`["ethUsdPriceFeed"]`
we're going to save this to eth USD price feed address.
我们要把这个保存到 `ethUsdPriceFeedAddress`
And now no matter what chain we're on, whenever we run hard hat deploy,
现在无论我们是在哪条链上，只要我们运行 `hardhat deploy`
if I run yarn, hard hat deploy dash dash network Rinkeby.
如果我运行 `yarn hardhat deploy --network rinkeby`
This chain ID is going to be four.
这个 "chainId" 就会是 4
And so it's going to use this price feed address.
接着它就会使用这一个喂价地址
If I do dash test network polygon, and I remember to add both ring P and polygon to my networks, like here,
如果我运行 `--network polygon`，当然，要记得在把 Rinkeby 和 Polygon 都添加到 "networks" 里
the channel is going to be 137. It's going to use this price feed address.
"chainId" 就会是 137 并使用这个喂价地址
So this is awesome. This is exactly what we want.
真是太棒了，这正是我们想要的
But is it everything that we want?
但这是我们想要的全部么？
Those of you who have been questioning while I have been coding and talking,
也许会有人在我编码和讲话时产生疑问
you might be thinking, Okay, well, you talked about this marking thing. You talked about localhost and hard hat.
你可能在想，OK 你提到了 mocking 还提到了本地主机和 Hardhat
And how do we test this locally?
但我们该怎么在本地做测试呢？
Like this is how we go to a test net and a main net.
这些都是在告诉我们怎么去测试网或者主网上
But what about a local network?
但是本地网络呢？
And that is exactly what we're going to talk about now.
这正是我们现在马上要讨论的东西
So we've modularized, our code and parameterize our code
我们已经模块化和参数化了我们的代码
so that we're going to use the address based off of the chain that we're on.
这样我们就可以基于我们所处的链来使用对应的地址了
But what if we use a chain that doesn't even have a price feed address on it?
但如果我们使用的链甚至都没有喂价地址呢？
What do we do there? This is where we actually create those mock contracts.
那我们该怎么办？这就是我们要创建 "mock" 合约的地方了
The idea of mock contracts here is if the contract doesn't exist,
"mock" 合约的想法是，如果某个合约不存在
we deploy a minimal version of it for our local testing, or our local testing.
我们就部署一个最小化的版本来进行我们的本地测试
And deploying mocks is technically a deploy script.
部署 "mock" 从技术上来说也是一个部署脚本
So what we do actually
我们实际上做的就是
is back in our deploy folder is we're going to create a new file,
回到我们的 "deploy" 文件夹，创建一个新文件
and we're going to call it 00 Dash deploy mocks dot j s,
我们将其命名为 "00-deploy-mocks.js"
we started with 00. Because this is almost like the pre deploy stuff,
我们从 00 开始是因为这几乎就是一个预部署的东西
we only do this, sometimes we don't always deploy mocks, right,
我们只是有时候这么做，并不会总是部署 "mock" 对吧？
we don't need to deploy mocks to Rinkeby, or polygon or or Aetherium main net,
我们不需要把 "mock" 部署到 Rinkeby 或 Polygon 或以太坊主网
because those already have these price feeds,
因为他们都已经有喂价数据了
we're actually going to deploy our own mock price feed contracts.
我们要部署一个自己的 "mock" 喂价合约
And in our deploy Funmi script,
在我们的 "deploy-fund-me" 脚本里
we're going to use our own contracts, instead of already established contracts.
我们要使用我们自己的合约，而不是已建立的合约
If we're on a network that doesn't have any price, few contracts,
如果我们在一个没有任何喂价合约的网络上
like hard hat or locos, for example.
比如说像 Hardhat 本体主机
So let's write our deploy mock script.
让我们开始编写我们的 "deploy-mocks" 脚本
So the setup of this is going to look nearly identical to our deploy Funmi.
这里的配置和我们的 "deploy-fund-me" 几乎相同
And again, if you want to set it up like this, you absolutely can.
当然，如果你想用这种方式进行设置，完全是可以的
But I'm actually just going to copy this, this part, paste it in here,
但我会选择复制这部分，粘贴到这里
because that initial part is going to be exactly the same.
因为初始部分是完全相同的
Oh, and over here, I just realized that we're calling this network thing without being defined,
哦，这个地方，我们正在调用这个 `network` 但没有定义
JavaScript will kind of be smart enough to know where this network thing is coming from.
JavaScript 很智能，知道这个 `network` 来自哪里
But it can be a little bit confusing.
但这可能会让人产生一点疑惑
So it's better to be really explicit,
所以最好还是明确一点
and say, const. Network equals require hard hat,
写下 `const  = require("hardhat")`
this network thing is coming from hard hat.
这个 `network` 来源于 "hardhat"
And we're going to grab this line. And we're also going to use this
我们复制这一行，因为这里也要使用它
at the top of our script here.
放到我们脚本的顶部
And then our top section is going to look exactly the same as well,
这样顶部的部分看起来就完全一样了
we're going to grab these three lines, and paste them in
我们复制这三行，然后粘贴过来
deploy deployer chain ID, boom, it's all going to be the same here,
`deploy deployer chainId`，boom，这里也完全一样
because we're setting up to deploy some stuff.
因为我们正在配置部署一些东西
Now we want to deploy a new contract.
现在我们想要部署一个新的合约
But if we look at our contracts folder, this is all we have right now.
查看一下我们的 "contracts" 文件夹，这就是目前我们所拥有的全部了
So we're going to need to add this mock this fake contract to our contracts folder.
所以我们需要添加这个 "mock" 虚拟合约到我们的 "contracts" 文件夹中
Now what we can do is in our contracts folder,
现在我们要在 "contracts" 文件夹中
we want to separate this file from the rest of our file
将这个文件与其它文件分离开来
so that we know okay, this isn't part of our project, but it is part of our testing.
这样我们就能知道，它并不是我们项目的一部分，而是用来进行测试的部分
So we're going to right click Create New Folder.
所以我们要右键，点击新建文件夹("Net Folder")
And we can either call it mocks, or test I like to call mine test.
我们可以将其命名为 "mocks" 或者 "test"，我喜欢用 "test"
And inside of this folder, we can go ahead and right click create a new file,
在这个文件夹里，我们继续右键点击新建文件("New File")
I'm going to create a new file and call it mock, v3 aggregate tore that soul.
我们将创建一个新文件并命名为 "MockV3Aggregator.sol"
And this is where we're going to define our mock price feed aggregator ourselves.
这就是我们用来定义我们自己的 "mock" 喂价聚合器的地方
So how can we create our own fake price feed contract,
那么我们该如何创建自己的虚拟喂价合约
so we can test everything locally?
以便能够进行所有的本地测试呢？
Well, one thing we could do is we go to the chain link GitHub repo,
其中一个可用的方法是，前往 Chainlink 的 GitHub 仓库
and go through the contracts and find one of these price feed addresses,
并进入 "contracts" 找到一个 "priceFeedAddress"
source eight, or maybe we'll go back to source
"src/v0.8"，或者我们先回到 "src"
we'll maybe we'll check in V six.
也许我们会选择 "v0.6"
Looks like we could find some stuff and look around
看起来我们可以找到一些东西并进行查看
and we probably copy paste all this code,
或许我们可以复制粘贴这里的全部代码
but it really seems like kind of a huge pain in the butt to have to copy all this code.
但这真的是有些麻烦，我们必须复制这里全部的代码
Now we absolutely could we copy paste the code in here,
我们当然可以把所有代码都复制粘贴过来
but we're gonna do something a little bit more clever.
但我们有更聪明的做法可以选择
So the chainlink repo actually comes with some mocks.
Chainlink 的仓库里其实就带有一些 "mock"
If we go to contracts, SRC V 0.6 tests
如果我们前往 "contracts/src/v0.6/tests/"
They actually have a mock v3 aggregator dot soul in here that we can use as our mock.
他们其实有一个 "MockV3Aggregator.sol" 在这里，我们可以将其用作我们的 "mock"
So we can copy paste everything,
我们可以复制粘贴所有内容
but we'd have to revamp a little bit of it
但我们必须对其进行一点修改
because it's doing some dot dot stuff.
因为它正在进行某些操作
It's talking to other contracts that are locally in this file structure
它正在与此文件架构中的其它本地合约进行交互
that are not going to be in our file structure.
而这些合约并不会出现在我们的文件结构中
So instead though, what we can do is we can use this node modules package to our advantage,
我们可以利用这个 "node_modules" 包来帮我们处理
we can just say pragma, solidity, carrot zero, point 6.0,
我们可以写下 `pragma solidity ^0.6.0;`
we'll use the same version that that package is doing.
我们要使用和这个包相同的版本
And then just do import at a chain link slash contracts slash SRC slash v 0.6. Slash tests slash mock, B, three egg, Reg, gay tore that soul.
然后是 `import @chainlink/contracts/src/v0.6/tests/MockV3Aggregator.sol`
And then we'll add, and then of course, we'll add spdx, license identifier, MIT.
当然了，还需要添加 `SPDX-License-Identifier: MIT`
And boom, this is actually all we need.
嘭，这就是我们所需要的全部了
If we just import the code like this,
如果我们只像这样导入这些代码
remember, this is exactly the same as copy pasting this contract into our project,
记住，这与将此合约复制粘贴到我们的项目中完全相同
of course, with this path resolve to where it actually is in our node modules.
当然，需要将其路径解析为实际在我们 "node_modules" 中的位置
Now, actually, I can run yarn hardhat compile,
现在，我们就可以执行 `yarn hardhat compile`
and it will also compile this contract.
它同样也会编译这个合约
Except for of course, we have an issue,
当然了，我们还会遇到问题
hey, compiler versions don't match. Right? What's What's up with that
嘿，编译器版本不匹配，对吧？这是怎么回事
now, you're going to get into situations
现在，你将会遇到这样的情况
where you will be working with contracts that are not the same version of solidity as you
你调用的合约使用与你不同版本的 Solidity
why well because contracts keep being deployed all the time.
为什么呢？因为合约在任何时候都可以部署
And there are a ton of contracts that are in version 0.4, solidity, 0.5 0.678,
因此会有大量合约使用 "0.4" 版本的 Solidity，也会有 "0.5" "0.6\7\8"
and probably 910, or 15 billion, or however many solidity versions will come to be.
大概还会有 "0.9\10" 甚至是 150 亿，或是任何将要出现的 Solidity 版本
So in our config, in our hard hat dot config,
所以在我们的配置文件 "hardhat.config" 中
when you scroll to the bottom,
我们可以滑到底部
we can scroll to where we're defining our solidity version.
滑到定义 Solidity 版本的地方
And we can actually add multiple solidity versions,
其实我们可以添加多个 Solidity 版本
so that our compiler can compile multiple versions of solidity.
这样我们的编译器就可以编译多个版本的 Solidity
To do that, we'll say, so Lyd, did T.
为此，我们要写 `solidity`
And we'll turn it into an object here,
我们要把它转换为一个对象
we'll make sure to put this comma here.
不要忘了这里还有一个逗号
And inside our solidity object, we'll put compilers
在我们的 `solidity` 对象内部写下 `compilers`
and we'll have a list of compilers.
我们会有一个 `compilers` 的列表
Our first one we'll say is version, zero, point 8.8.
第一个，我们告诉它 `version: "0.8.8"`
And we'll say our second one is going to be version 0.6, point six,
然后第二个是 `version: "0.6.6"
and then we'll go ahead and save that.
接着我们保存一下
And it looks like mine wanted to format it like this, which is fine.
看来我的格式化方式是这样的，很不错
Now, we can go ahead, rerun, yarn, Hardhead, compile,
现在我们就可以继续了，重新运行 `yarn hardhat compile`
and boom, compiled five solidity files successfully.
嘭，成功编译了五个 Solidity 文件
This means that our Mark V aggregator should also have been compiled.
这意味着我们的 "MockV3Aggregator" 应该也编译好了
And if we look in artifacts, at chain link,
如果我们查看 "artifacts/@chainlink"
do indeed see this at chain link slash contract slash SRC bid, and a v 0.6. In tests,
我们确实可以看到在 "@chainlink/contracts/src/v0.6/tests" 下
we see this mock aggregator dot soul, which has been compiled.
有一个 "MockV3Aggregator.sol"，已被编译
Awesome. So now that we have our mock contract compiled,
太好了，现在我们的 "mock" 合约已经编译好了
we now have a contract that we can use to deploy a fake price feed to a blockchain.
现在我们拥有了一个将虚拟喂价合约部署到区块链上的合约
So how do we actually do this?
现在我们该怎么做
Well, it's going to be the exact same way that we deployed the Funmi contract.
其实就和我们部署 "FundMe" 合约的方法几乎完全一样
But we're going to add a little if statement in here,
区别就是我们要在这里添加一个 "if" 语句
we don't want to deploy this mock contract to a test net or a network that actually has a price feed on it,
我们不打算把这个 "mock" 合约部署到测试网或是已经有喂价数据的网络上
we could just do something like if chain ID does not equal, you know, some chain ID, then deploy marks, right.
我们可以这么做 `if (chainId != )` 某些 "chainId" 然后就 `deploymocks`
And then this is kind of pseudocode. Obviously, this code won't actually work.
当然这是一种伪代码，它们是无法实际运行的
But instead, what I like is I actually like to specify
相反，我喜欢指定
which chains are going to be my development chains,
哪些条链是我的开发链
which chains are going to be the one that I can deploy these mocks to,
哪些链是我要部署 "mock" 的链
in my helper, hard hat config, I'll define these chains.
在我的 "helper-hardhat-config" 中，我会定义这些链
So I'll say const, development chains, equals,
因此我会写下 `const developmentChain = `
and then I'll just say hard hat, and local host.
接着我会说有 "hardhat" 以及 "localhost"
I'll export these. And back in my deploy mocks,
我会导出它们，然后回到我的 "deploy-mocks"
I'll import these with const. Development chains equals require dot dot slash helper Hardhead config.
导入它们 `const  = require("../helper-hardhat-config")`
And now I'll say if development chains dot includes chain ID.
现在我要写下 `if (developmentChains.includes(chainId))`
This includes keyword basically is a function that checks to see
这个 `includes` 关键字就是一个函数，它会检查
if some variable is inside an array,
如果某些变量在某个数组中
then we're gonna go ahead and deploy Max, and which is what we want to do.
我们就继续部署 "mock"，这正是我们想做的
So we'll do log, which we're getting from deployments, which is basically console dot log.
执行 `log()`，这是从 "deployments" 中获取的，基本就等于 `console.log`
And we'll say local network detected, deploying mocks.
我们会说 "Local network detected! Deploying mocks..." (“检测到本地网络！部署 mocks...”)
And we'll do a weight ploy,
接着就是 `await deploy()`
and we'll deploy our new mock v3 aggregator
部署我们的新 "MockV3Aggregator"
mock v3 aggregator will do a comma. There a little colons here.
"MockV3Aggregator" 后面是逗号，然后是冒号(应为括号)
If we want to get really specific,
如果我们想比较具体
we can say contract v3 aggregator which we're kind of already saying
就这么说 `contract: "MockV3Aggregator"` 某种程度上我们已经这么说了
we'll say from deployer
然后是 `from: deployer`
We'll say logging is going to be true.
`log: true`
And then we need to pass some arguments,
接着我们需要传递一些参数
we need to pass the constructor parameters for the mock v3 aggregator, which are what?
我们要为 "MockV3Aggregator" 的构造函数传递参数，应该是什么呢？
Well, let's go to docs chain to link to find out.
让我们前往 "docs.chain.link" 寻找答案
Or you can also just go to Node modules chainlink, SRC V 06, tests,
或者你可以转到 "node_modules/@chainlink/src/v0.6/tests"
and then all the way down to mock V three, aggregated out. So
然后找到 "MockV3Aggregator.sol"
where you could also find the constructor in here,
你也可以在这里找到构造函数
whatever one you like better, sometimes I find it easier just to read GitHub
你喜欢哪一个用哪一个就好，有时候我觉得去 GitHub 找更容易一些
Ctrl plus F or Command plus F for constructor.
"Ctrl + F" 或者 "Command + F" 搜索 "constructor"
We see it takes a decimals and an initial answer.
我们看到，它需要一个 "_decimals" 和一个 "_initialAnswer"
And if we read through the code,
如果我们通读代码
we'll learn that the decimals object is going to be equivalent to
就会了解到 "_decimals" 对象就等同于
the decimals parameter is going to be equivalent to this decimals function
"_decimals" 参数就等同于这个 "decimals" 函数
and the initial answer. And the initial answer is basically just going to be what is the price feed starting at,
而这个 "_initialAnswer" 基本上就是喂价是多少的意思
we actually get to pick the price of the price feed,
我们可以指定喂价的价格
which works out really well, because that works out great for testing.
这一点非常好，因为这样很好测试
I usually like to define the decimals and the initial answers somewhere outside of this function
我通常喜欢把 "_decimals" 和 "_initialAnswer" 的定义放到函数之外
so that I can access it later.
这样我以后就能随时访问它们了
One good place you can add it is once again in our helper Hardhead config.js.
一个添加它们的好地方是，又一次是我们的 "helper-hardhat-config.js"
So I might do const decimals equals eight.
我可能会写 `const DECIMALS = 8`
And then const initial answer. Answer equals, and we'll do 2000.
然后是 `const INITIAL_ANSWER = 2000`
So since we have a decimals, we'll do 2000
既然我们的 "DECIMALS" 是 8 这里我们就取 2000
And then 123456788 decimal places,
后面是 12345678，8 个小数位
and then we'll export these as well. Export decimals, and export initial answer.
然后我们同样把它们导出出来，导出 `DECIMALS` 以及 `INITIAL_ANSWER`
We could of course, just do you know, const decimals equals eight at the top
当然了，我们也可以把 `const DECIMALS = 8` 放到顶部
and then initial answer and then use them down here.
然后下面是 `INITIAL_ANSWER`
But I like to do it like that.
但我更喜欢刚才那样做
So Conce. So now we have to import them in here.
const development chains. It's also grabbed decimals.
It's also grabbed initial answer, we'll save it.
We'll take a look back at the constructor looks like it's decimals first, initial answers second.
So in our arguments, we'll do decimals first, initial answers second,
and tada. And then we will be all done
that we'll do a quick log box deployed.
And then I also like to do kind of like a big line at the end of all of my deploy scripts
just to be like, hey, that's the end of this deploy script.
Anything else after this is going to be a different deploy script.
All right, great. Now our deployed mocks script is actually done.
But our deploy Funmi script isn't quite done.
Is there a way that we could run only our deploy mock script?
Well, yes, there is. Great, thanks for asking.
What we can do at the bottom of our deploy mock script
is we can add a module that exports dot tags, equals, and we'll say all and marks.
Now what we can do is if we run yarn, hard hat deploy, we can add this flag dash dash tags.
And it will only run the deploy scripts that have a special tag.
So we'll run our mocks tag, which means it'll only run our deploy mock script.
And, and oops, actually, in our helper config
development chains is actually hard hat and localhost.
And I said, we're going to try to do with the chain ID,
sorry, we're going to do this,
we're gonna do development chains dot includes network dot name.
Because our helper config is using names and not chain IDs,
so if development chains that includes that network the names,
then we're gonna go ahead and deploy the mocks.
So let's go ahead and run this yarn here and hit Deploy dash dash tags, mocks.
And perfect we do indeed see our mocks getting deployed here.
This log true means that it's going to spit out stuff like this.
It'll say contract, it's deploying, it'll say the transaction it's doing
and it'll say where it was deployed with how much gas
and awesome This means our deployed Mach script is working perfectly.
So now we have our deploy mocks script working perfectly.
So how do we apply that back to our deploy Funmi script?
Well, we're gonna do the exact same thing here.
Instead of making eth USD price feed address constant variable,
we're gonna say let at USD price you'd variable
so that we can actually update it.
And we'll say, if development chains dot includes network dot name,
what we can do with hard hat deploy
is we can just get the most recent deployment using a command called literally get.
So we'll say const. eth USD aggregator equals await deployments dot get.
And then the name of the contract that we deployed Mach v3 aggregator,
and if you wanted to just do get instead of deployments dot get,
we absolutely could, just by doing it like this.
Those are exactly the same.
So we'll get the address like this and then we'll say
eth USD price feed address equals that eth USD aggregator contract dot address.
And then if we're not on a development chain,
if we didn't deploy a mock, we're just going to do exactly what we did before.
With using the network config.
Oh, my goodness. Now, now that we've done all of these steps,
let's add a little log thing at the bottom here with just a bunch of hyphens.
Now, we should have a very robust script
to flip between a local development chain, a test net chain, a main net chain,
and allow us to deploy literally everywhere without changing any of our solidity.
And then we just take this, this eth USD price feed address and stick it into logs here.
And then at the bottom, we can do module dot exports, dot tags equals
and then we'll just do all
and then we'll call this one Funmi.
Oh, now moment of truth. If we did all this, right,
we should just be able to run yarn, hard hat deploy.
And it should work on our local chain, our hard hat chain.
And then it should also work on any test net that we give it.
So let's give this a try. Yarn, Hardhead deploy. Let's see if this works.
Awesome. And we got this all to deploy locally to our Hard Hat Network,
we can see that we went ahead and we deployed mocks, we did our little underline here.
And then we deployed Funmi deployed at this address with this much gas.
Now, what are the other awesome things about hard hat deploy?
When we run our local blockchain, our own blockchain node,
hard hat deploy will automatically run through
all of our deploy scripts and add them to our node.
So now if I run yarn, hard hat node,
we're going to spin up a new blockchain node,
but it's already going to have all of our deployed contracts on it.
So every time we spin up a local node, now
it's going to come automatically packed with the contracts that we want on it.